[Music]
thanks to curiosity stream for
supporting PBS Digital Studios just
kidding hey I'm Diana you're watching
physics girl and last week I got to hang
out with contortionist and youtuber
Sophie dossie we did some science
experiments for her channel and while we
were hanging out I realized that as a
physicist I know absolutely nothing
about what stretching does to your body
and whether there's a scientifically
supported way of becoming more flexible
there is stay tuned I didn't know so I
headed over to USC to meet with a bio
mechanist to find out the latest science
I'm Michael Rowley I am a PhD candidate
in the division of bio kinesiology and
physical therapy my first question was
is there something different about
Sophie yes yes very different but I mean
like biomechanically does she have a
superpower there's evidence that people
who are hyper flexible quick pause hyper
flexible or hyper mobile is actually a
scientific term and there's a test used
to determine whether someone is hyper
flexible it's called the Buyten score
and I'll link to it in the description
if you want to test yourself okay so
people who are a hypermobile those
people have a little bit more relatively
of the of the more stretchy collagen
than the type one collagen uh-huh I need
a quick refresher on collagen take it
away Michael
so a bone to bone connection is a
ligament and then a muscle to bone
connection is the tendon tendons and
ligaments are made up of mostly collagen
which is a type of protein and there's
different types of collagen so tendons
and ligaments have primarily type one
collagen which is a really strong type
and then also some type 3 collagen which
will be more
stretchy and then may also include some
elastin which is another type of
connective tissue that's very elastic
and stretchy so the ratios of those
things can be different I got it so
Sophie might actually have a different
material makeup of the tissues in her
body like she might have more of that
type three collagen which would allow
her to do things that the average person
can't do back wise I almost can't over
stretch anymore because I'm just
completely in half yeah so it's like I
have push women on that like there's
just I mean you can't you can't you're
not a ghost you're not a ghost you know
but how flexible is Sophie
yeah before I started contortion I was
always more flexible than that average
gymnast yes yeah when I was little I
used to watch TV with my feet over my
head yeah that's flexible okay but how
do you get flexible biomechanically I
guess my first question is when you
stretch what parts of your body are
stretching out yeah so when you stretch
you're gonna increase flexibility and
excursion in all those tissues muscles
tendons ligaments the most short term
the fastest most acute effects will be
in the muscle so your tendons and your
ligaments are stretching out to how does
that work they seem so dirty this is
getting to the heart of what I really
really want to know which is what is
physically happening to all of these
tissues the actual pieces of physiology
that change with stretching the body
will change the water content in the
material that's probably the fastest way
and then you can also induce some stem
cells that still live in the tendon
material themselves and those can
differentiate into more cells they can
produce more or slightly different types
of fibrillar proteins like that collagen
that I talked about so your body can
change the material properties of your
tissues by stretching cool another way
is that you actually modify sensation so
you might experience some mild pain the
first time you're going to stretch but
you'll actually desensitize yourself to
that pain over repeated stretching
multiple days a week for multiple we
hold up yes one way of getting more
flexible is just becoming more numb to
pain it actually really feels good it
feels like a nice good stretch it
doesn't feel like a hurt stretch at all
crazy I have no chance another change
that happens physiologically with
stretching our muscles have an alpha
gamma a reflex loop so when you stretch
a muscle there's this automatic signal
that gets sent to the spinal cord it
doesn't even go up to the brain and back
the spinal cord then tells the muscle to
contract that Co activation would be bad
for stretching right if you're
stretching the muscle and then the
muscles trying to pull back on you so
over time you can actually down regulate
that reflex loop and that's been shown
to happen when you stretch for long
periods of time lastly you actually add
length to the muscle fibers you do that
by adding sarcomeres which are sort of
the the contractile unit producing the
active contraction of muscles Wow bodies
are so complicated so let's recap
stretching can change the water content
in your muscles stem cell
differentiation how much you feel pain
that alpha gamma reflex loop from your
muscles to your spinal cord and the
length of your muscle fibers that's cool
now I know what's going on when you get
more flexible biomechanics is cool
almost as awesome as physics may be more
useful though which brings me my last
question what does science have to say
about how to get more flexible well
Michael pointed me to this really
interesting meta analysis which is like
a big study that actually synthesizes
all the findings from other studies in
this case 23 other studies which looked
at how to get the best benefits on
improved range of motion or flexibility
and they found that static stretching
that is when you ease into a stretch and
then hold it for 30 to 60 seconds that's
the best for improved range of motion or
flexibility and as far as how much to
stretch they found that 5 minutes total
per week of one muscle group was sort of
the lower limit but you didn't see much
more of a benefit over 10 minutes a week
of stretching and six days out of the
week was the plateau of seeing returns
so the more you stretch per day doesn't
keep increasing the benefits but that
frequency six days a week and then the
five minutes total for that week is why
it's important so commence operation
stretching muscle group for six
he's a week five minutes total now of
course different types of stretching
have different benefits so I will link
to some of the other literature in the
description but more importantly in the
description is the video that I did over
with Sophie on her channel I channeled
my inner youtuber and we did a challenge
where all the science experiments I was
doing Sophie had to do with her feet
she's insane it was amazing I had so
much fun filming with her so check out
that video and subscribe to Sophie's
Channel and thank you to Michael at USC
who blew my mind with biomechanics facts
physicists don't get to learn a whole
lot of biomechanics and that's it
subscribe to physics girl if you want to
learn more stuff with me that I'm
randomly interested in every couple
weeks thank you so much for watching and
happy physics thing I'd like to thank
curiosity stream for supporting PBS how
did you do this oh I'd like to thank
curiosity stream for supporting PBS
Digital Studios
curiosity stream is a subscription
streaming service that offers
documentaries and nonfiction titles from
some of the world's best filmmakers
including exclusive regionals I would
recommend watching dream the future
which is a new 19 part series about what
the future is gonna be like what's it
gonna be like when we do sports when
there's exoskeletons and big data plus
it's narrated by Sigourney Weaver Oh get
unlimited access and for our audience
the first 60 days are free when you sign
up a curiosity stream comm slash physics
girl and use promo code physics girl
during the signup process
[Music]